Actually, I come from Britain,
بالواقع أنا من بريطانيا,
but I've been living in Maldives for 26 years now.
لكنني مازلتُ أعيش في المالديف منذ 26 سنة.
So, that's home really.
لذا, ذلك موطني حقيقة.
The Maldives, as I'm sure you're aware, are a chain of islands
المالديف، كما تعلمون، سلسلة من الجزر
off the southwest coast of India here.
مقابل الساحل الجنوب الغربي من الهند.
Capital, Malé, where I live.
عاصمتها ماليه، حيث أعيش.
Actually, sitting here today in Mysore,
في الواقع مكاننا حيث نجلس الآن في "مايسور"
we're closer to Malé than we are to Delhi, for example.
نحن أقرب لماليه من دلهي، على سبيل المثال.
If you're in IT, India, obviously, is the place to be at the moment.
إن كنت تعمل في مجال تقنية المعلومات، فالهند، بطبيعة الحال، هي أفضل مكان لك حالياً.
But if you're a marine biologist, Maldives is not such a bad place to be.
ولكن، إن كنت عالم أحياء بحرية، فوجودك في المالديف ليس أمراً سيئاً على الإطلاق.
And it has been my home these years.
وقد كانت مقري سكني طوال هذه السنين.
For those of you who've been there, fantastic coral reefs,
من زارها يعرف روعة شعابها المرجانية،
fantastic diving, fantastic snorkeling.
ومتعة الغوص والغطس في بحارها.
I spend as much of my time as possible
أنا أقضي كل الوقت الذي يمكنني قضاؤه
investigating the marine life.
دارساً للكائنات البحرية.
I study fish,
أدرس السمك،
also the bigger things, whales and dolphins.
وأدرس الكائنات الكبيرة أيضاً، كالحيتان والدلافين.
This is a blue whale. We have blue whales
هذا حوت أزرق. لدينا حيتان زرقاء
in the waters around here, off Maldives,
في المياه المحيطة بالمالديف،
around the waters of India. You can see them off Kerala.
وفي المياه المحيطة بالهند. يمكننا أن نراها أيضاً على سواحل ولاية كيرلا (الهندية).
And, in fact, we're very lucky in this region.
وفي الواقع، نحن محظوظون جداً في هذا الإقليم.
One of the best places in the world to see blue whales
أحد أفضل الأماكن في العالم لرؤية الحيتان الزرقاء
is here in this region.
موجود هنا في هذا الإقليم.
In Sri Lanka, if you go down to the south coast of Sri Lanka,
في سريلانكا، إن ذهبت إلى سواحلها الجنوبية،
during the northeast monsoon season,
خلال فترة هبوب الرياح الموسمية الشمالية الغربية،
you can see blue whales very, very easily.
يمكنك رؤية الحيتان الزرقاء بسهولة بالغة.
It's probably the best place in the world to see them.
لعله أفضل مكان في العالم لرؤيتها.
Now, when I talk about the northeast monsoon season,
الآن، حين أتحدث عن فترة هبوب الرياح الموسمية الشمالية الشرقية
I'm sure many of you here know exactly what I mean,
فأنا متأكد من أن أغلبكم يعرف بالضبط ما أقصده،
but perhaps some of you are not quite so sure.
ولكن لعل بعضكم غير متأكد.
I need to explain a little bit about monsoons.
علي أن أتحدث أكثر عن الرياح الموسمية.
Now, monsoon, the root of the word "monsoon"
كلمة "مونسون" الإنجليزية، جذر هذه الكلمة،
comes from the word "season."
يأتي من كلمة "موسم".
So, it's just a season. And there are two seasons in most of South Asia.
إذاً، هي مجرد موسم. وفي جنوب آسيا، يوجد موسمان.
And in the summer India heats up, gets very hot.
وفي الصيف تزداد الحرارة في الهند، يصبح الجو حاراً جداً.
Hot air rises, and air is drawn in off the sea to replace it.
يرتفع الهواء الحار، ويتم سحب الهواء من فوق البحر بدلاً منه.
And the way it works is, it comes from the southwest.
وكيفية عملها هو أن الهواء يأتي من الجنوب الغربي.
It comes off the ocean here and is drawn up towards India.
يتم سحب هذا الهواء من فوق المحيط هنا نحو الهند.
So it comes from the southwest. It's a southwest monsoon.
إذاً الهواء يأتي من الجنوب الغربي. إنه رياح موسمية جنوبية غربية.
Picks up moisture as it crosses the ocean.
تحمل هذه الريح الرطوبة حين تمر فوق المحيط.
That's what brings the monsoon rain.
وهذا ما يأتينا بالأمطار الموسمية.
And then in the winter things cool down.
ثم في فصل الشتاء تزداد البرودة.
High pressure builds over India.
ينشئ فوق الهند ضغط عالي.
And the whole system goes into reverse.
وما يجعل المنظومة بأكملها تنعكس.
So, the wind is now coming from the northeast
أي، أن الرياح الآن تأتي من الشمال الشرقي
out of India, across the Indian Ocean,
خارجة من الهند، عبر المحيط الهندي،
this way towards Africa.
بهذا الاتجاه نحو أفريقيا.
Keep that in mind.
ابقوا ذلك في أذهانكم.
Now, I'm a marine biologist, but I'm actually
الآن، أنا عالم أحياء بحرية. إلا أنني في الواقع
a bit of an old fashioned naturalist, I suppose.
أكاد أكون باحثاً طبيعياً تقليدياً، كما أظن.
I'm interested in all sorts of things, almost everything that moves,
أنا مهتم بأشياء متعددة، كل شيء يتحرك تقريباً،
including dragonflies. And I'm actually
مثل حشرات اليعسوب. في الحقيقة
going to talk, this afternoon, about dragonflies.
سأتحدث، ظهر هذا اليوم، عن الحشرات.
This is a very beautiful species, it's called the Oriental Scarlet.
إنها كائنات جميلة جداً، يسمونه القرمزي الشرقي.
And one thing you need to know about dragonflies,
وما يجب أن تعلمونه عن اليعسوب،
one important thing,
أمر مهم جداً،
is that they lay their eggs in fresh water.
هو أنها تضع بيضها في المياه العذبة.
They need fresh water to breed.
إنها بحاجة إلى المياه العذبة لتتكاثر.
They lay the eggs into fresh water.
فهي تضع بيضها في المياه العذبة.
Little larvae hatch out in fresh water.
يرقات صغيرة تفقس في المياه العذبة.
They feed on other little things. They feed on mosquito larvae.
تعتمد اليرقات على أشياء صغيرة أخرى للتغذية. إنها تتغذى على يرقات البعوض.
So, they're very important.
إذاً، هي مهمة جداً.
They control mosquito larvae, among other things.
إنها تسيطر على تعداد يرقات البعوض، بالإضافة لأمور أخرى.
And they grow and grow by stages. And they climb out
وتواصل نموها عبر مراحل. ثم تتسلق خارج
of the water, burst out, as the adult which we see.
الماء، وتتدفق، في مرحلة البلوغ التي نراها.
And typically, there is a lot of variation,
وعادة، يوجد الكثير من الاختلاف،
but if you have a dragonfly with, say, a one year life cycle,
ولكن إن كان لدينا يعسوب له، مثلاً، دورة حياتية ذات سنة واحدة،
which is quite typical, the larva, living in the fresh water,
وهو أمر معتاد، اليرقات، التي تعيش في المياه العذبة،
lives for 10 or 11 months.
تعيش لعشر أو إحدى عشر شهراً.
And then the adult, which comes after, lives for one or two months.
وبعد ذلك يعيش اليعسوب البالغ لشهر أو شهرين.
So it's essentially a freshwater animal.
أي، هو بالضرورة حيوان يعتمد على المياه العذبة.
It really does need fresh water.
إنه بحاجة ماسة للماء العذب
Now, the particular species of dragonfly
الآن، النوع المحدد من اليعسوب
I want to talk about is this one,
الذي أود الحديث عنه هو هذا،
because most dragonflies, like the one we've just seen,
لأن معظم اليعسوب، كالذي رأيناه قبل قليل،
when the adult is there for its brief one or two months of life,
حين يتواجد الناضج لفترة قصيرة - شهر أو شهرين على قيد الحياة،
it doesn't go very far. It can't travel very far.
إنه لا يذهب بعيداً. إنه لا يستطيع السفر لمسافات طويلة.
A few kilometers, maybe, is quite typical.
بضع كيلوميترات، وهو أمر معتاد.
They are very good fliers, but they don't go too far.
إنهم ماهرون في الطيران، ولكنهم لا يغطون مسافات طويلة.
But this guy is an exception.
إلا أن هذا استثناء.
And this is called the Globe Skimmer,
يسمونه متصفح الكرة الأرضية،
or Wandering Glider.
أو الطائرة الشراعية المتجولة.
And, as the name might suggest, it is found pretty much around the world.
ويمكننا أن نجده في معظم أنحاء العالم، وهو ما يوحي به لنا اسمه.
It lives throughout the tropics, the Americas,
إنه يعيش في في المناطق الاستوائية، والأمريكتين،
Africa, Asia, Australia, into the Pacific.
وأفريقيا، وآسيا، وأستراليا، والمحيط الهادي.
And it wanders far and wide. We know that much about it.
وتتجول طولاً وعرضاً. هذا ما نعرفه حتى الآن.
But it really hasn't been studied very much.
إلا أنه لم يُدرَس كما يجب.
It's a rather mediocre looking dragonfly.
نحن ننظر إلى يعسوب يبدو أنه دون المتوسط.
If you're going to study dragonflies, you want to study those really bright beautiful ones,
إن كنت تنوي دراسة اليعسوب، فإنك تود دراسة اليعسوب المضيء الجميل،
like that red one. Or the really rare ones, the endemic endangered ones.
مثل تلك الحمراء. أو تلك النادرة جداً، تلك المعرضة للانقراض في أوطانها.
This is, it seems a bit dull you know.
أما هذا، فيبدو مملاً كما تعلمون.
It's sort of dull-colored. And it's fairly common.
لونه يبعث للملل. وهو متواجد بكثرة.
And it occurs everywhere -- you know, why bother?
ونراه في كل مكان -- فلماذا نوليه أي اهتمام؟
But if you take that attitude, you're actually missing something rather special.
إن اتخذت هذا الموقف، فأنت تفوت على نفسك أمراً مميزاً.
Because this dragonfly has a rather amazing story to tell.
لأن هذا اليعسوب يملك قصة جميلة ليرويها لك.
And I feel very privileged to have stumbled across it
وأشعر أنني محظوظ حين وقعت صدفة على قصته
living in the Maldives.
أثناء عيشي في الملاديف.
When I first went to the Maldives,
حين ذهبت إلى الملاديف أول مرة،
dead keen on diving, spent as much of my time
عاقداً العزم على الغوص، قاضياً معظم وقتي
as I could in and under the water.
في الماء وتحت سطحه.
Didn't notice any dragonflies; maybe they were there, maybe they weren't.
لم ألاحظ اليعاسيب; ولا أهتم بوجودها من عدمه.
Didn't notice them.
لم ألاحظها.
But after some time, after some months, one day
ولكن بعد بعض الوقت، بعض بضع شهور، في يوم ما
as I was going out and about,
حين كنت أخرج للتنزه،
suddenly I noticed hundreds of dragonflies, hundreds of dragonflies.
لاحظت فجأة مئات اليعاسيب، مئات اليعاسيب.
Something like this, these are all this species Globe Skimmer.
شيء كهذا، هذه كلها من هذه فصيلة متصفح الكرة الأرضية.
I didn't know at the time, but I know now,
لم أكن أعلم وقتها، ولكنني أعلم الآن،
they're Globe Skimmers, hundreds of them.
إنهم متصفحو الكرة الأرضية، المئات منهم.
And they were there for some time. And then they were gone.
وكانوا موجودين لفترة. ثم اختفوا.
And I didn't think anything more of it until
ولم أفكر بها أكثر من ذلك إلى
the following year, when it happened again,
العام التالي، حين حدث نفس المشهد مرة أخرى،
and then the year after that, and then the year after that.
ثم في السنة التالية، ثم في السنة التالية لها.
And I was a bit slow, I didn't really take too much notice.
وكان استيعابي بطيئاً، ولم أبدِ لها أي اهتمام.
But I asked some Maldivian friends and colleagues, and yes they come every year.
ولكني سألت بعض أصدقائي وزملائي من المالديف، وأكدوا تكرار ذلك كل سنة.
And I asked people about them and yes,
وسألت الناس عن ذلك ونعم،
they knew, but they didn't know anything,
يعلمون بذلك، ولكنهم لم يعلموا شيئاً،
where they came from, or anything.
من أين أتت، أو أي شيء.
And again I didn't think too much of it.
ومرة أخرى لم أبدِ أي اهتمام.
But slowly it began to dawn on me that something
ولكن ببطىء اتضح لي، أن شيئاً
rather special was happening.
متميزاً جداً يحدث.
Because dragonflies need fresh water to breed.
لأن اليعسوب يحتاج لمياه عذبة للتكاثر.
And the Maldives, and I'm sure some of you have been there --
و المالديف، وأنا متأكد أن بعضكم زارها --
so here is home.
إذاً، هنا المنزل.
So, Maldives, beautiful place.
إذاً، المالديف، مكان جميل.
(Laughter)
(ضحك)
It's built entirely of coral reefs.
يتكون بالكامل من الشعاب المرجانية
And on top of the coral reefs are sand banks.
وفوق الشعاب المرجانية تلال رملية.
Average height, about that much above sea level.
متوسط الارتفاع، هذا القدر فوق مستوى البحر
So, global warming, sea level rise, it's a real serious issue.
إذاً، احتباس حراري، ارتفاع مستوى الماء، إنها قضية خطيرة.
But I'm not going to talk about that.
ولكني لن أتحدث عن ذلك.
Another important point of these sand banks
أمرٌ آخر مهم عن هذه التلال الرملية
is that when it rains,
هو أنها حين تمطر
the rainwater soaks down into the soil. So, it's gone.
تتخلل مياه الأمطار التربة. إذاً، تختفي.
So, it stays under the soil.
إذاً، المياه تحت التربة.
The trees can put their roots into it.
يمكن لجذور الأشجار أن تنمو فيها.
Humans can dig holes and make a well.
يمكن للبشر حفرها من أجل الآبار.
But dragonflies -- a bit tricky.
أما اليعسوب -- فالأمر ماكر بعض الشيء.
There is no surface fresh water.
لا توجد مياه عذبة سطحية.
There are no ponds, streams, rivers, lakes,
لا توجد بِرَك، ولا جداول، ولا أنهار ولا بحيرات،
nothing like that.
لا شيء من هذا القبيل.
So, why is it that every year
إذاً، لماذا كل سنة
millions of dragonflies, millions,
الملايين من اليعسوب، الملايين،
millions of dragonflies turn up?
الملايين من اليعسوب تظهر فجأة.
I got a little bit curious. In fact I'll stop here,
أصابني شيء من الفضول. في الحقيقة سأقف هنا،
because I want to ask, and there is a lot of people who,
لأني أريد أن أسأل، ولأنه يوجد الكثيرون ممن،
from India of course, people who grew up spending your childhood here.
من الهنود بالطبع، ممن قضوا جزءاً من طفولتهم هنا.
Those of you who are Indian or spent your childhood here,
الهنود منكم أو من قضوا طفولتهم في هنا في الهند،
let me have a show of hands, who of you --
ارفعوا أياديكم لنرى، من منكم --
not yet, not yet!
ليس الآن، ليس الآن!
You're too keen. You're too keen. No. Hang on. Hang on.
حماسكم زائد. حماسكم زائد. لا. انتظروا. انتظروا.
Wait for the go. I'll say go.
انتظروا إلى حين أقول "هيا". سأقول "هيا".
Those of you who grew up in India,
الذين ترعرعوا في الهند،
do you remember in your childhood, dragonflies,
هل تذكرون في طفولتكم، اليعسوب،
swarms of dragonflies? Maybe at school,
حشد من اليعسوب؟ ربما في المدرسة،
maybe tying little bits of string onto them?
ربما ربطتم خيوط صغيرة عليهم؟
Maybe pulling bits off? I'm not asking about that.
ربما قطعتموهم إرباً إرباً؟ لا اسألكم عن ذلك.
You've only got to say, do you remember seeing lots of dragonflies.
كل ما عليكم قوله، هل تذكرون رؤية الكثير من اليعاسيب.
Any hands? Any hands? Yes. Thank you. Thank you.
أين الأيادي المرفوعة؟ أين الأيادي المرفوعة؟ شكراً. شكراً.
It's a widespread phenomenon
إها ظاهرة منتشرة
throughout South Asia, including the Maldives.
في ربوع جنوب آسيا، بما في ذلك المالديف.
And I got a bit curious about it.
وبدأ الفضول ينتابني عن ذلك.
In the Maldives -- now, in India there is plenty of water,
في المالديف، والآن في الهند تتوفر المياه بكثرة،
so, dragonflies, yeah, of course. Why not?
إذاً، اليعاسيب، نعم، بالطبع. لمَ لا؟
But in Maldives, no fresh water. So, what on Earth is going on?
ولكن في المالديف، لا توجة مياه عذبة. إذاً، ماذا تفعل هنا بالضبط؟
And the first thing I did was started recording
وأول شيء فعلته هو بدأت تسجيل
when they turned up in the Maldives.
أوقات ظهورها في المالديف.
And there is the answer, 21st of October.
وظهر لي الجواب، ٢١ أكتوبر/تشرين أول.
Not every year, that's the average date.
ليس كل سنة، هذا متوسط التواريخ.
So, I've been writing it down for 15 years now.
إذاً، أنا أسجل ذلك منذ ١٥ سنة حتى الآن.
You'd think they're coming from India. It's the closest place.
قد تعتقد أنها تأتي من الهند. أقرب الأماكن.
But in October, remember, we're still in southwest monsoon,
ولكن في أكتوبر، تذكروا، ما زلنا في خضم الرياح الموسمية الجنوبية الغربية،
Maldives is still in the southwest monsoon.
المالديف ما زالت تتعرض للرياح الموسمية الجنوبية الغربية.
But wind is, invariably, every time, is from the west.
ولكن الرياح، برتابة، كل مرة، تأتي من الشرق.
It's going towards India, not from India.
إنها متجهة إلى الهند، ولا تأتي منها.
So, are these things, how are these things getting here?
إذاً، هل هذه الأشياء، كيف تصل هذه الأشياء إلى هنا؟
Are they coming from India against the wind?
هل تأتي من الهند بعكس اتجاه الرياح؟
Seemed a bit unlikely.
بدا ذلك مستبعداً قليلاً.
So, next thing I did is I got on the phone.
إذاً، رفعت سماعة الهاتف.
Maldives is a long archipelago.
المالديف أرخبيل طويل.
It stretches about 500 miles, of course it's India here.
يمتد لمسافة ٥٠٠ ميل تقريباً، طبعاً هنا الهند.
I got on the phone and emailed to friends and colleagues.
رفعت السماعة واتصلت على أصدقاء وزملاء.
When do you see the dragonflies appear?
متى تلاحظون ظهور اليعاسيب؟
And pretty soon, a picture started emerging.
وبعد قليل، بدأت الصورة تتضح.
In Bangalore, a colleague there sent me
في بانغلور، أرسل إليَّ زميل
information for three years, average,
معلومات تمسح ٣ سنوات، متوسط،
24th of September, so late September.
٢٤ سبتمبر/ز\أيلول، إذاً قرب نهاية سبتمبر.
Down in Trivandrum, a bit later.
في مدينة فاننتابورام، تتأخر قليلاً.
Far north of Maldives, a bit later.
في أقصى شمال المالديف، تتأخر قليلاً.
Then Malé, then further south.
ثم في العاصمة ماليه، ثم أبعد جنوباً.
And then the southernmost Maldives.
ثم في أقصى جنوب المالديف.
It's pretty obvious, they're coming from India.
الأمر واضح جداً، إنها تأتي من الهند.
But they are coming 400 miles across the ocean, against the wind.
ولكنها تعبر 400 ميل في المحيط، بعكس اتجاه الرياح.
How on Earth are they doing that?
كيف يمكنها فعل ذلك.
I didn't know.
لم أعلم.
The next thing I did was I started counting dragonflies.
ما فعلته بعد ذلك هو عدُّ اليعاسيب.
I wanted to know about their seasonality,
أردت معرفة موسميتها،
what time of year, this is when they first arrive,
في أي وقت من السنة، هنا يكون بداية ظهورها،
but how long are they around for? Does that give any clues?
ما مدة بقاؤها؟ هل يعطني ذلك المزيد من الدلائل؟
So, I started a very rigorous scientific process.
لذلك، بدأت عملاً علمياً شديد الصرامة.
I had a rigorous scientific transect.
عملت على تقسم العمل بشكل علمي صارم.
I got on my bicycle,
امتطيت دراجتي،
and I cycled around the island of Malé.
وقدتها حول جزيرة مالييه.
It's about five kilometers around,
مسافة ٥ كيلومترات،
counting the dragonflies as I go,
أعدُّ اليعاسيب طوال الوقت،
trying not to bump into people as I'm looking in the trees.
محاولاً تفادي الاصطدام بالناس أثناء نظري إلى الشجر.
And they're here for a very short time,
وهي تظل هنا لفترة قصيرة جداً،
October, November, December. That's it.
أكتوبر/تشرين الأول، نوفمبر/تشرين الثاني، ديسمبر/كانون الأول. فقط.
And then they tail off, there's a few, but that's it.
ثم يبدأون بالاختفاء، يبقى القليل، ولكن هذا كل شيء.
October, November, December. That is not the northeast monsoon season.
أكتوبر/تشرين الأول، نوفمبر/تشرين الثاني، ديسمبر/كانون الأول. هذا ليس موسم الرياح الموسمية الشمالية الشربية.
That's not the southwest season.
وليس موسم الرياح الجنوبية الغربية.
That's the inter-monsoon,
إنه موسم ما بين مواسم الرياح الموسمية،
the time when the monsoon changes.
الوقت الذي يتغير فيه اتجاه الرياح.
Now, what I said was, you get the southwest monsoon going one way,
الآن، ما قلته هو، ستجدون الرياح الموسمية الجنوبية الغربية في اتجاه،
and then it changes and you get the northeast monsoon going the other way.
ثم تتغير وتجدون الرياح الموسمية الشمالية الشرقية في الاتجاه الآخر.
And that sort of gives the impression you've got one air mass
وهذا يعطي الانطباع بأن لديك كتلة هوائية واحدة
going up and down, up and down. It doesn't work like that.
ترتفع وتنخفض، ترتفع وتنخفض. هذا انطباع خاطئ.
What happens, actually, is there is two air masses.
ما يجري، في الواقع، هو أن لدينا كتلتين هوائيتين.
And there is a front between them, and the front moves.
وتوجد جبهة هوائية بينهما، وهذه الجبهة تتحرك.
So, if you've got India here,
إذاً، إن كانت الهند هنا،
when the front is up above India you're into the southwest monsoon.
حين تكون الجبهة الهوائية فوق الهند نحو الرياح الموسمية الجنوبية الغربية.
Then the front moves into the northeast monsoon.
ثم تتحرك الجبهة الهوائية نحو الرياح الموسمية الشمالية الشرقية.
And that front in the middle is not vertical,
وهذه الجبهة في الوسط ليست عمودية،
it's at an angle.
بل على زاوية.
So, as it comes over towards Malé
إذاً، حين تعبر الجبهة فوق ماليه
I'm standing in Malé underneath the front.
أنا أقف في ماليه تحت الجبهة.
I can be in the southwest monsoon.
قد أكون في وسط الرياح الموسمية الجنوبية الغربية.
But the wind above is from the northeast monsoon.
إلا أن الرياح فوقي هي من الرياح الموسمية الشمالية الغربية.
So, the dragonflies are actually coming from India on the northeast monsoon,
إذاً، هذه اليعاسيب تأتي من الهند على متن الرياح الموسمية الشمالية الشرقية.
but at an altitude at 1,000 to 2,000 meters up in the air. Incredible.
ولكن على ارتفاع 1000 إلى 2000 متر في الهواء. مذهل.
These little insects, it's the same ones we see out here [in India],
هذه الحشرات الصغيرة، والتي ترونها هنا [في الهند]،
two inches long, five centimeters long,
لا يزيد طولها عن بوصتين، خمس سنتمترات،
flying in their millions, 400 miles across the ocean,
تطير الملايين منها، 400 ميل عبر المحيط،
at 2,000 meters up. Quite incredible.
بارتفاع ألفي متر. مذهل جداً.
So, I was quite pleased with myself. I thought wow, I've tracked this one,
إذاً، كنت مسروراً جداً مع نفسي. اندهشت، تتبعت هذه،
I know how they come here. Then I scratched my head a bit,
أعلم كيف يأتون هنا. ثم حككت رأسي قليلاً،
and that's okay,
وهذا جيّد،
I know how they come here, but why do they come here?
أعرف كيف يأتون هنا، ولكني لا أعرف لماذا يأتون إلى هنا؟
What are millions of dragonflies doing, flying out over the ocean every year
ماذا تفعل الملايين من اليعاسيب، عابرةً المحيطات كل عام
to their apparent doom?
متجهة نحو حتفها؟
It doesn't make sense. There is nothing for them in Maldives.
هذا غير منطقي. لا يوجد شيئ لها في المالديف.
What on Earth are they doing?
ماذا يفعلون؟
Well, to cut a long story short,
في الحقيقة، ولنختصر قصتها الطويلة،
they're actually flying right across the ocean.
هي في الواقع تطير فوق المحيط.
They're making it all the way across to East Africa.
إنها تطير إلى شرق أفريقيا.
I know that because I have friends who work on fisheries' research vessels
أعرف ذلك عن طريق أصدقائي الذين يعملون في مسامك سفن الأبحاث
who have sent to me reports from boats out in the ocean.
والذين أرسلوا لي تقارير من السفن في وسط المحيط.
I know because we have reports from Seychelles,
أعرف ذلك لأن لدي تقرير من السيشيل،
which fit in as well, down here.
وهي تتطابق مع ملاحظاتي، هنا.
And I know because
وأعلم ذلك لأنه
when you look at the rainfall,
حين تنظر إلى سقوط الأمطار،
these particular insects, these Globe Skimmers
هذه الحشرات بالذات، متصفحي الكرة الأرضية
breed in temporary rain water pools.
تتكاثر في برك مؤقتة ناتجة عن سقوط الأمطار.
Okay, they lay their eggs where the seasonal rains are,
حسناً، إنها تلد بيضها حيث تسقط الأمطار الموسمية،
the monsoon rains.
أمطار الرياح الموسمية.
The larvae have to develop very quickly.
يجب على اليرقات أن تنمو بسرعة.
They only take six weeks. Instead of 11 months, they're six weeks.
لا يستغرق ذلك سوى ست أسابيع. بدل 11 شهراً يحتاجون ست أسابيع،
They're up, and they're off.
تفقس ثم تنطلق.
Now, here we have, in case you can't read at the back,
الآن، هنا لدينا، في حالة أنكم لم تقرأوه في الخلف،
the top is rainfall for India.
في الأعلى تساقط أمطار في الهند.
And we're starting in June. So this is the monsoon rain.
ونحن نبدأ في يونيو/حزيران. إذاً هذه أمطار موسمية.
By September, October, it's drying out.
عندما يحين سبتمبر/أيلول، أكتوبر/تشرين الأول، تبدأ بالجفاف.
Nothing for these dragonflies. There is no more seasonal rain.
لا شيء لهذه اليعاسيب. ولا مزيد من الأمطار الموسمية.
They've got to go hunting for seasonal rain.
عليهم البحث عن الأمطار الموسمية.
And they fly south. As the monsoon withdraws to the south
ويطيرون نحو الجنوب. فيما تنسحب الرياح الموسمية نحو الجنوب
they come down through Karnataka, into Kerala.
يعبرون خلال كارناتاكا، إلى كيرلا.
And then they run out of land.
ثم تنفذ اليابسة تحتهم.
But they are incredibly good fliers. This particular species,
إنهم ماهرون جداً في الطيران. هذا النوع بالذات
it can fly for thousands of kilometers.
يستطيع الطيران آلاف الكيلومترات.
And it just keeps going. And the wind, the northeast wind
وتواصل رحلتها. والرياح الشمالية الشرقية
swooshes it around and carries it off across the ocean to Africa,
تحملها معها عبر المحيط إلى أفريقيا،
where it's raining.
حيث تمطر.
And they are breeding in the rains of Africa.
وتبدأ بالتزاوج في أمطار أفريقيا.
Now, this is southeast Africa. It makes it look like there are sort of
الآن، هذا جنوب شرق أفريقيا. إنها تجعل الأمر يبدو
two breeding periods here. It's slightly more complicated than that.
وكأن هناك فترتي تزاوج هنا. الأمر أكثر تعقيداً من ذلك.
What's happening is they are breeding in the monsoon rains here.
ما يحدث هو أنها تتزاوج في الأمطار الموسمية هنا.
And the dragonflies you can see today
واليعاسيب التي ترونها اليوم
outside here, on the campus,
في الخارج، في الحرم الجامعي،
are the young of this generation.
هي نسل هذا الجيل.
They hatched out in India.
فقسوا في الهند.
They're looking for somewhere to breed. If it rains here they'll breed.
إنهم يبحثون عن مكان للتزاوج. إن أمطرت ستتزاوج.
But most of them are going to carry on. And next stop,
إلا أن معظمها ستواصل. والمحطة المقبلة،
perhaps only four or five days away is going to be East Africa.
ربما بعد أربع أو خمس أيام ستكون شرق أفريقيا.
The wind will swoosh them out across here.
ستلقي بهم الرياح إلى هنا.
If they pass the Maldives they might go and have a look,
إن مروا على المالديف فقد تلقي نظرة،
nothing there, they'll carry on.
لا يوجد شيء، سيواصلون.
Here, here, Kenya, East Africa,
هنا، هنا، كينيا، شرق أفريقيا
they've actually just come out of a long drought.
لتوهم خرجوا من قحط طويل.
Just last week the rains broke. The short rains broke
لتوها هطلت الأمطار الأسبوع الماضي. هطلت أمطار قصيرة الأمد
and it's raining there now.
وهي تمطر هناك الآن.
And the dragonflies are there. I have reports from my various contacts.
واليعاسيب هناك. لدي تقارير من الكثيرين.
The dragonflies are here now. They're breeding there.
اليعاسيب هنا الآن. وهي تتزاوج هناك.
When those guys, they'll lay their eggs now.
حين يقوم هؤلاء، سيضعون بيضهم الآن.
They'll hatch out in six weeks. By that time
ستفقس خلال ست أسابيع. في ذلك الحين
the seasonal rains have moved on. It's not there, it's down here.
ستنتقل الأنطار الموسمية. ليست هناك، بل هنا.
They'll fly down here. And the clever thing is
سيطيرون إلى هنا. واللمحة الذكية هي
the wind is always converging to where the rain is.
أن الرياح تلتقي في نقطة واحدة حيث توجد الأمطار.
The rain occurs, these are summer rains.
تنزل الأمطار، هذه أمطار صيفية.
This is a summer monsoon.
هذه الرياح الموسمية الصيفية.
The sun is overhead there. Summer rains in southern Africa.
الشمس فوقنا هناك. الأمطار الصيفية في جنوبي أفريقيا.
The sun is overhead, maximum heating,
الشمس فوقنا، الحرارة على أشدها،
maximum evaporation, maximum clouds,
التبخر على أشده، والغيوم على أشدها،
maximum rainfall,
الأمطار على أشدها،
maximum opportunities for reproduction.
أي أفضل الفرص للتكاثر.
Not only that, because you have this convection,
ليس ذلك فقط، لدينا أيضاً انتقال للحرارة،
you have this rising of the air
الهواء يرتفع
where it's hot, air is drawn in.
حيث الطقس ساخن، يتم سحب الهواء.
There's a convergence. So, wherever the rain is falling,
لديك تلاقي الرياح. إذاً، حيثما يهطل المطر
the air is drawn towards it to replace the air that's rising.
يتم سحب الهواء لتعويض الهواء الصاعد.
So, the little fellow that hatches out here,
إذاً، حين يفقس اليعسوب الصغير هنا،
he gets up into the air, he is automatically carried
فإنه يصعد في الهواء، ويُحمَل تلقائياً
to where the rain is falling.
حيث يهطل المطر.
Lay their eggs, next generation, they come up,
تضع البيض، الجيل القادم، يصعدون،
automatically carried to where the rain is falling.
محمولة تلقائياً إلى حيث تهطل الأمطار.
It's now back there. They come out, it's time to come back.
الآن عادت إلى هناك. إنها تخرج، ثم يحين وقت العودة.
So, in four generations, one, two, three,
إذاً، خلال أربع أجيال، واحد، اثنان، ثلاثة،
four and then back.
أربعة ثم العودة.
A complete circuit of the Indian Ocean.
دورة كاملة للمحيط الهندي.
This is a circuit of about 16,000 kilometers.
طول الدورة 16,000 كيلومتراً.
16,000 kilometers, four generations, mind you,
16,000 كيلومتراً، أربع أجيال، اسمحوا لي،
for a two inch long insect. It's quite incredible.
لحضرة طولها بوصتين. هائل جداً.
Those of you from North America
الحضور القادمون من أمريكا الشمالية
will be familiar with the Monarch butterfly.
يعرفون الفراش الملكي.
Which, up until now has had the longest known insect migration.
والتي إلى اليوم، تملك أطول مسار هجرة لحشرة معروف لنا.
It's only half the length of this one.
مسارها لا يزيد على نصف مسار اليعاسيب.
And this crossing here, of the ocean,
وهذا العبور، فوق المحيط
is the only truly regular transoceanic crossing
هو العبور المحيطي الطبيعي الحقيقي الوحيد
of any insect.
لأي حشرة.
A quite incredible feat.
إنه عمل هائل.
And I only stumbled on this because I was living in Malé,
ووقعت عليه لأنني عشت في ماليه،
in Maldives for long enough
في المالديف لفترة كافية
for it to percolate into my brain
ليستوعب عقلي
that something rather special was going on.
أن شيئاً مميزاً يحدث.
But dragonflies are not the only creatures that make the crossing.
ولكن اليعاسيب ليست المخلوقات الوحيدة التي تحقق هذا العبور.
There is more to the story.
القصة أطول من ذلك.
I'm also interested in birds. And I'm familiar
أنا مهتم بالطيور. وأنا أعرف
with this fellow. This is a rather special bird.
هذا الطائر. إنه طائر مميز.
It's a falcon. It's called the eastern red-footed falcon, obviously.
إنه طائر الباز. يُسمى الباز ذي الأقدام الحمراء الشرقي، كما هو واضح.
But it's also called the Amur Falcon.
ولكنه يسمى أيضاً صقر العمورية.
And it's called the Amur Falcon
ويسمى صقر العمورية
because it breeds in Amurland.
لأنه يتزاوج في عمّورلاند.
Which is an area along the Amur River, which is up here.
القريبة من نهر عمّور، الواقع هنا.
It's the border, much of it is the border
إنها الحدود، أغلبها الحدود
between China and Russia, up here in the far east.
بين الصين وروسيا، هنا في الشرق الأقصى.
So, Siberia, Manchuria.
إذاً، سيبيريا، مانشوريا.
And that's where it breeds.
وهنا تتزاوج.
And if you're a falcon it's quite a nice place to be in the summer.
وإن كنت طائر باز فإنه مكان جيد لقضاء الصيف.
But it's a pretty miserable place to be in the winter.
إلا أنه مكان بمنتهى السوء لقضاء الشتاء.
It's, well, you can imagine.
إنه، يمكنكم التخيل بطبيعة الحال.
So, as any sensible bird would do,
إذاً، سيفعل الباز ما سيفعله أي طائر عاقل،
he moves south. They move south. The whole population moves south.
إنه ينتقل إلى إلى الجنوب. إنها تنتقل إلى الجنوب. ينتقل السرب بأكمله إلى الجنوب.
But then the being sensible stopped.
إلا أن العقلانية تتوقف هنا.
So, now they don't stop here, or even down here.
إذاً، هي لا تتوقف هنا، أو حتى هنا.
No, they turn across here.
لا، إنهم ينحرفون عابرين هنا.
They have a little refueling stop in northeastern India.
ولديهم محطة للراحة في شمال شرق الهند.
They come to the latitude of about Mumbai or Goa.
ثم تصل إلى خط العرض المقارب لمومباي أو غوا.
And then they strike out across the ocean, down to Kenya.
ثم تنطلق عبر المحيط، إلى كينيا.
And down here, and they winter down here [in southern Africa].
هنا، وتقضي الشتاء هنا [في جنوبي أفريقيا].
Incredible. This is the most extraordinary migration
هائل. هذه الهجرة عظيمة جداً
of any bird of prey. A quite incredible migration.
لأي طائر جارح. إنها فعلاً هجرة هائلة.
And they are not the only one that makes the crossing.
وهم ليسوا فقط القادرين على مثل هذا العبور.
They have the most incredible journey, but several make the crossing from India
لديهم أكثر الرحلات إثارة، ولكن غيرهم يقوم بالعبور من الهند
to Africa. Includes this one, the hobby.
إلى أفريقيا. منهم هذا، الصقر.
This fellow is a very nice bird, this is the Pied cuckoo.
هذا طائر جميل جداً، هذا الوقواق الرزين.
Those of you from northern India will be familiar with this.
القادمون من شمالي الهند يعرفون هذا الطائر.
It comes with the monsoons.
إنه يأتي مع الرياح الموسمية.
This time of year they cross back to Africa.
في هذا الوقت من العام تعبر إلى أفريقيا.
And this guy, the roller, a rather beautiful bird.
وهذا الطائر، الشقراق، طائر جميل جداً.
It's known as the Eurasian Roller. In India it occurs in the northwest,
معروف باسم الشقراق الأوراسيوي. في الهند يظهر في الجزء شمال الشرقي،
so it's known as the Kashmir Roller.
لذلك تُعرَفُ هناك باسم الشقراق الكشميري.
And these birds, what I've done is I've complied all the records,
ومع هذه الطيور، ما فعلته أنني قمت بجمع كل السجلات،
all the available records of these birds,
كافة السجلات المتعلقة بهذه الطيور،
put them together, and found out they migrate at exactly the same time
جمعتها ببعضها، واكتشفت أنها تهاجر في نفس الوقت
as the dragonflies.
مع اليعاسيب.
They make use of exactly the same winds.
إنهم يستفيدون من الرياح ذاتها.
They travel at exactly the same time with the same winds
إنها تسافر في نفس الوقت مع نفس الرياح
to make the crossing. I know they travel at the same altitude.
لتقوم بعملية العبور. أنا أعلم أنها تتنقل على نفس خط العرض.
It's known about the Amur Falcon. This guy, unfortunately,
يُعرَفُ هذا باسم صقر العمورية. للأسف
one of these met an unfortunate end.
قابل أحد هذه الصقور نهاية مأساوية.
He was flying off the coast of Goa,
كان يطير فوق ساحل غوا،
21 years ago, 1988. October, 1988.
قبل 21 سنة، 1988، أكتوبر/تشرين الأول 1988.
An Indian Navy jet was flying off Goa,
كانت مقاتلة من البحرية الهندية تطير فوق غوا،
bang! In the middle of the night. Fortunately, a two engine jet
وتعطل محرك، في منتصف الليل، ولحسن الحظ يوجد محرك آخر،
got back to base, and they pulled the remains of one of these [Eurasian Rollers] out.
عادت المقاتلة للقاعدة، وأخرجوا بقايا [شقراق أوراسياوي].
Flying at night over the Indian Ocean 2,424 meters.
يطير في الليل فوق المحيط الهندي بارتفاع 2,424 متر.
Same height as the dragonflies go.
بمثل ارتفاع طيران اليعاسيب.
So, they are using the same winds.
إذاً، هي تستخدم الرياح نفسها.
And the other thing, the other important factor
والأمر الأخر، العامل المهم الآخر
for all these birds, all medium sized fellows,
لكل هذه الطيور، كلهم متوسطي الحجم،
and this includes the next slide as well, which is a bee-eater.
هذا يشمل الشريحة التالية، آكل النحل.
Bee-eaters eat bees. This one has a nice blue cheek.
آكلات النحل تأكل النحل. هذا لديه خد أزرق جميل.
It's a Blue-cheeked Bee-eater.
أنه آكل نحل ذا خطين أزرقين.
And every one of these birds that makes the crossing
وجميع أفراد هذه الفصيلة تعبر
from India to East Africa
من الهند إلى شرق أفريقيا
eats insects, large insects,
وتأكل الحشرات، خصوصاً الكبيرة،
the size of dragonflies. Thank you very much.
بحجم اليعاسيب. شكراً جزيلاً.
(Applause)
(تصفيق)